Guide to the James H. Laue papers, 1936-1999
George Mason University Libraries
- Series 5: Academic Papers, 1947-1990
  - Subseries 5.2: Professional Papers, 1966-1999, bulk 1971-1993
    - "Third Party Intervention in Community Disputes: A Review of the Experience to Date", 1973 (Box 85, Folder 4)
      by Gerald W. Cormick and James Laue, 40 pages
    - Thomas Jefferson Award, April 1981 (Box 85, Folder 5)
      correspondence, newsletters, and press releases re: Laue receiving the Jefferson Award
    - United States Information Agency, 1987 (Box 85, Folder 6)
      Bureau of Educational And Cultural Affairs University Affiliations Program application notice
    - University City Schools News, June 9, 1980 (Box 85, Folder 7)
    - University of Missouri-St. Louis (UMSL) Annual Review and Notes, 1980-1982 (Box 85, Folder 8)
      correspondence, CVs, news clippings, and articles re: Laue's annual academic review
    - UMSL Annual Reviews, 1977-1987 (Box 85, Folder 9)
    - UMSL Annual Reviews and Tenure Application, 1978-1982 (Box 86, Folder 1)
    - UMSL Application Materials for Promotion to Full Professor, 1981-1982 (Box 86, Folder 2)
    - UMSL Files, 1975-1979 (Box 86, Folder 3)
    - UMSL Files, 1980-1982 (Box 86, Folder 4)
    - UMSL Files, 1983-1986 (Box 86, Folder 5)
    - UMSL Promotion Update, 1982-1985 (Box 86, Folder 6)
    - UMSL Summer Institute in Conflict Intervention, June-July 1985 (Box 86, Folder 7)
    - UMSL Tenure Proceedings, 1976-1977 (Box 87, Folder 1)
    - "The Vertical Axis of Community Organization and the Structure of Power", ca. 1965 (Box 87, Folder 2)
      essay by John Walton, 20 pages
    - VUD - Correspondence, Notes, and Newsletters, 1983-1984 (Box 87, Folder 3)
      UMSL, Urban Affairs Association, JSAC, Sociology of Education
    - Washington University-St. Louis Associate Professorship Confirmation, 1971-1972 (Box 87, Folder 4)
    - Washington University-St. Louis - "Report on Work of the Campus Publications Study Committee", 1973-1974 (Box 87, Folder 5)
    - Wisconsin State University-River Falls (WSU-RF) Commencement Address - "Is Hope Hip?" by James Laue, May 24, 1970 (Box 87, Folder 6)
    - WSU-RF Commencement - Distinguished Alumnus, 1978 (Box 87, Folder 7)
    - WSU-RF - News and Notes, 1966-1971 (Box 87, Folder 8)
    - WSU-RF - Race Course, Spring 1973 (Box 87, Folder 9)
    - Working Outline and Publisher Report for the Conflict Resolution Handbook, 1989 (Box 87, Folder 10)
      edited by James Laue and Robert K. Reed
- Series 6: Conferences and Workshops, 1962-1992
  This series contains programs, presentations, notes, and correspondence pertaining to various conferences and workshops Laue attended or administered. The folder dates in this series generally refer to the dates the conferences were held and may not encompass the date range of all materials in the folder. Ranging from small local workshops to large international meetings, the conferences cover a range of themes including desegregation, clinical sociology, community conflict intervention, international arbitration, and peace education. Series 7, News Clippings and Articles, contains newspaper articles collected and assembled by Laue. Themes include desegregation and civil rights, international politics, biographical pieces and interviews with Laue, and the peace academy campaign. The series is divided into two subseries, the first arranged by date and the second arranged alphabetically by subject or newspaper title.
  - Airlie House Conference, June 19-22, 1988 (Box 87, Folder 11)
    Arlie, Virginia - USIP
  - American Sociological Association Annual Meeting, Session 167, September 7, 1978 (Box 87, Folder 12)
    contains draft copies of Laue's conference paper, "Development of a U.S. Academy of Peace and Conflict Resolution"
  - Bishop's Convocation on Peace and National Security, 1981-1984 (Box 87, Folder 13)
  - Black Mountain Conference on Race Relations and the Church, August 20-24, 1962 (Box 88, Folder 1)
    hosted by the Provincial Youth Commission of the Diocese of North Carolina
  - Broadening Our Horizons: Second Annual Arizona Conference on Dispute Resolution, November 6-7, 1987 (Box 88, Folder 2)
    Tucson, Arizona
  - "Building a Fresh Approach to Peace and Security", 1987 (Box 88, Folder 3)
    Report on the 1987 Trinity Symposium Policy Dialogue
  - Call for Action Conference, part 1 of 2, April 28-29, 1981 (Box 88, Folder 4)
    Boston, Massachusetts
  - Call for Action Conference, part 2 of 2, April 28-29, 1981 (Box 88, Folder 5)
  - Center for International Understanding Conferences, 1981-1982 (Box 88, Folder 6)
    Athens, Greece / Jerusalem, Israel
  - Christian Faith and Economic Justice: A Workshop on Reconciliation and Conflict Resolution, September 20-23, 1990 (Box 88, Folder 7)
    Northfield, Illinois
  - Clinical Sociological Association Training Workshop on Intervening in Social Conflict, part 1 of 2, April 12-14, 1984 (Box 88, Folder 8)
    workshop led by James Laue at the University of Missouri-St. Louis
  - Clinical Sociological Association Training Workshop on Intervening in Social Conflict, part 2 of 2, April 12-14, 1984 (Box 88, Folder 9)
  - Collaboration and Conflict Resolution in Community Problem Solving, March 16-17, 1988 (Box 89, Folder 1)
    Washington, DC; Conflict Clinic, Inc.
  - Community Conflict Intervention Workshop: Framing a New Discipline, July 30 - August 28, 1974 (Box 89, Folder 2)
    Seattle, Washington; Social Science Institute and Batelle Research Center
  - Community Dispute Resolution Conference, part 1 of 2, June 19-20, 1979 (Box 89, Folder 3)
    Cherry Hill, New Jersey
  - Community Dispute Resolution Conference, part 2 of 2, June 19-20, 1979 (Box 89, Folder 4)
  - Community Relations Service (CRS) Conference - Inter-religious consultation on Equal Opportunity: A Workshop, November 16-19, 1964 (Box 89, Folder 5)
    Arlie House; folder contains materials from the President's Committee on Equal Employment Opportunity, including a 150 Report to the President submitted on November 26, 1963
  - Conference on a National Academy for the Peaceful Resolution of Conflict, March 1-3, 1978 (Box 89, Folder 6)
    brief report and working paper
  - Conference on Conflict Resolution with Special Reference to Multicultural Conflict, January 6-8, 1986 (Box 89, Folder 7)
    Amsterdam - SIETAR
  - Conference on Mass Media and Race Relations, October 17-18, 1967 (Box 89, Folder 8)
    conference for CRS by the American Jewish Committee at Columbia University
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. Conference: A New Model for Dispute Resolution, December 13, 1983 (Box 89, Folder 9)
    St. Louis, Missouri
  - Conflict Resolution in the Post-Cold War Third World, October 3-5, 1990 (Box 89, Folder 10)
    USIP conference
  - Conflict Resolution Workshop Materials, 1980s-1992 (Box 89, Folder 11)
  - Defining a U.S. Negotiation Style, February 17, 1988 (Box 90, Folder 1)
    Virginia Center for Foreign Affairs
  - "Determining a Company's Social Commitments: An Informal Conference for Corporate Urban Affairs", January 20-21, 1971 (Box 90, Folder 2)
    Washington, DC; Public Affairs Council
  - Disharmony in the Local Church: Workshop on "The Bishop's Role as Conflict Resolver", May 3, 1989 (Box 90, Folder 3)
  - Eastern Sociological Society Panel on "The Sociologist-Activist in the Civil Rights Movement", April 9-11, 1965 (Box 90, Folder 4)
    New York
  - Educating for Peace? A Conference on a National Academy for the Peaceful Resolution of Conflict, March 1-3, 1978 (Box 90, Folder 5)
    Emory University
  - Farm Crisis Workshop, March 31 - April 1, 1986 (Box 90, Folder 6)
    Conflict Clinic
  - Getting to Peace: A Midwest Approach, May 29-30, 1986 (Box 90, Folder 7)
    Iowa City, Iowa
  - Getting to Peace: A Midwest Approach, May 22-23, 1987 (Box 90, Folder 8)
  - International Conference on Conflict Resolution in South Africa, Israel and Northern Ireland, September 8-12, 1989 (Box 90, Folder 9)
    Bonn, Germany
  - International Conference on Conflict Resolution in South Africa, Israel and Northern Ireland, September 9-13, 1989 (Box 90, Folder 10)
  - International Conference on Peacebuilding, April 28 - May 3, 1986 (Box 90, Folder 11)
  - International Negotiations Workshop at Harvard, July 9-13, 1984 (Box 91, Folder 1)
  - Iowa State University In-Service Training Workshop Dealing with Controversial Issues in Extension Education, June 6, 1979 (Box 91, Folder 2)
  - Middle Powers Conference, May 14-15, 1987 (Box 91, Folder 3)
  - Midwest Conference for the U.S. Institute of Peace, May 11, 1985 (Box 91, Folder 4)
    Loyola University of Chicago
  - Miscellaneous Conference Brochures and Flyers, 1970-1990 (Box 91, Folder 5)
  - National Association of Intergroup Relations Officials (NAIRO) National Conference on Human Rights Workers, September-October 1970 (Box 91, Folder 6)
    Tulsa, Oklahoma
  - National Conference on Peacemaking and Conflict Resolution, March 4-6, 1983 (Box 91, Folder 7)
    Athens, Georgia; conference organizers and final report
  - National Conference on Peacemaking and Conflict Resolution, March 4-6, 1983 (Box 91, Folder 8)
    Athens, Georgia; follow-up
  - National Conference on Peacemaking and Conflict Resolution, September 18-23, 1984 (Box 91, Folder 9)
    Athens, Georgia
  - National Conference on Peacemaking and Conflict Resolution, September 20-23, 1984 (Box 91, Folder 10)
  - National Conference on Peacemaking and Conflict Resolution: "Issues of an Emerging Field", September 20-23, 1984 (Box 91, Folder 11)
  - National Conference on Peacemaking and Conflict Resolution, June 5-8, 1986 (Box 92, Folder 1)
    Denver, Colorado
  - National Conference on Religion and Race, January 14-17, 1983 (Box 92, Folder 2)
    Chicago; includes older conference materials from 1962-1964
  - North American Conference on Peacemaking and Conflict Resolution, February 28 - March 5, 1989 (Box 92, Folder 3)
    Montreal, Canada
  - Northeast Region Conference on Citizen/Community Dispute Resolution, April 26-27, 1979 (Box 92, Folder 4)
    National Association for Dispute Resolution
  - Peace Corps Physicians Conference, September 11-13, 1970 (Box 92, Folder 5)
    Arlie House, Warrenton, Virginia
  - "Pragmatic Peacemaking: A Negotiation Workshop", December 14-15, 1987 (Box 92, Folder 6)
  - Program on Negotiation and the Conflict Clinic, Inc. Conference for Associates, October 19, 1984 (Box 92, Folder 7)
  - "Reducing the Dangers of International Conflict: The Rule of Law and Third-Party Mediation", undated (Box 92, Folder 8)
    meeting proposal
  - "Reflections of a Sociologist/Mediator on the Harvard Conference on Dispute Resolution, October 14-16, 1982 (Box 92, Folder 9)
  - Resolving Environmental Disputes through Mediation: A Workshop, October 28-30, 1974 (Box 92, Folder 10)
    Spokane, Washington
  - Sociological Perspectives on Global Conflict and Cooperation: A Research Agenda, February 14-16, 1985 (Box 92, Folder 11)
    Rancho Santa Fe, California
  - Southern Regional Education Board Conference on Urban Revolt, October 6-8, 1967 (Box 92, Folder 12)
    Atlanta, Georgia
  - Soviet-American Citizens' Summit, 1977-1978 (Box 92, Folder 13)
    Alexandria, Virginia
  - Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) Conference, October 14-16, 1960 (Box 92, Folder 14)
  - "Third Party Intervention in Community Conflict: Definitions, Perspectives and Experience", September 18-19, 1973 (Box 92, Folder 15)
    conference paper by James Laue and Gerald Cormick
  - U.N. Peacemaking and Peacekeeping: 20th U.N. Issues Conference, 1989 (Box 92, Folder 16)
    Harriman, New York
  - United States Institute of Peace (USIP) Grand Celebration and Inaugural Workshops, November 9-10, 1984 (Box 93, Folder 1)
    University of Hawaii at Manoa
  - Urban Community Conflict Intervention Meeting, June 27, 1973 (Box 93, Folder 2)
  - "The Use of Mediation in Environmental Disputes", November 12, 1974 (Box 93, Folder 3)
    paper by Jane E. McCarthy presented at the annual convention of the Society of Professionals in Dispute Resolution
  - Whitehouse Conference: "To Fulfill These Rights", November 16-18, 1965 (Box 93, Folder 4)
  - Whitehouse Conference: "To Fulfill These Rights": Council's Report and Recommendations to the Conference, June 1-2, 1966 (Box 93, Folder 5)
  - World Conference on Religion and Peace, ca. 1980 (Box 93, Folder 6)
  - World Congress on Peace: The Best Environment, October 25-28, 1985 (Box 93, Folder 7)
    Vienna, Austria
- Series 7: News Clippings and Articles, 1936-1992
  This series contains newspaper articles collected and assembled by Laue. Themes include desegregation and civil rights, international politics, biographical pieces and interviews with Laue, and the peace academy campaign. The series is divided into two subseries, the first arranged by date and the second arranged alphabetically by subject or newspaper title.
  - Subseries 7.1: News Clippings, Chronological, 1936-1992
    This subseries contains news clippings arranged by date.
    - News Clippings, 1930s-1960s (Box 93, Folder 8)
    - Newspapers, 1969-1970 (Box 93, Folder 9)
    - Newspapers, 1970s (Box 93, Folder 10)
    - Newspapers, 1980s (Box 94, Folder 1)
    - Newspapers, 1980s - early 1990s (Box 94, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 7.2: News Clippings, Alphabetical, 1960-1990
    This subseries contains news clippings arranged alphabetically by subject or title.
    - CBS Broadcast Excerpt, 1988 (Box 94, Folder 3)
      re: USIP
    - Chicano Protest, 1971 (Box 94, Folder 4)
    - China, 1982 (Box 94, Folder 5)
    - Civil Rights Scrapbook 1, February-March 1960 (Box 94, Folder 6)
      desegregation / sit-ins
    - Civil Rights Scrapbook 2, March 1960 (Box 94, Folder 7)
    - Civil Rights Scrapbook 3, April 1960 (Box 94, Folder 8)
    - Civil Rights Scrapbook 4, April-May 1960 (Box 94, Folder 9)
    - Cold War, Carbide Gas Leak in India, Service Economy, and Farm Assistance, 1986-1988 (Box 94, Folder 10)
    - Daily Kent Stater, 1978 (Box 95, Folder 1)
    - Footnotes: Newsletter of the American Sociological Association, 1982-1984 (Box 95, Folder 2)
    - GMU Enrollment Boom and Affirmative Action, 1987 (Box 95, Folder 3)
    - Heidegger Article with Annotations, 1962 (Box 95, Folder 4)
    - International Politics, Corruption, Racial Violence, and the Conflict Clinic, 1978-1982 (Box 95, Folder 5)
    - Manual for the Republican Convention, August 20-23, 1972 (Box 95, Folder 6)
      radical "Tactical Manual" published by the Red Buffalo Press
    - Mississippi Free Press - Civil Rights, part 1 of 3, 1962-1963 (Box 95, Folder 7)
    - Mississippi Free Press - Civil Rights, part 2 of 3, 1963-1964 (Box 95, Folder 8)
    - Mississippi Free Press - Civil Rights, part 3 of 3, 1964 (Box 95, Folder 9)
    - Negotiation and Mediation, 1986-1989 (Box 96, Folder 1)
    - News Clippings Featuring Laue, 1965-1975 (Box 96, Folder 2)
      CRS, Wisconsin State University-River Falls, Civil Rights
    - News Clippings, Notes and Interviews Featuring James Laue, 1978-1987 (Box 96, Folder 3)
    - Peace Academy Campaign, 1976-1979 (Box 96, Folder 4)
    - Peace Academy Campaign, 1979-1980 (Box 96, Folder 5)
    - Peace Academy Campaign, 1980 (Box 96, Folder 6)
    - Peace Academy Campaign, 1980-1981 (Box 96, Folder 7)
    - Peace Academy Campaign, 1982-1983 (Box 96, Folder 8)
    - Peace Academy Campaign, 1984 (Box 96, Folder 9)
    - Peace Corps Times, July-August 1980 (Box 96, Folder 10)
    - Pope's Visit, October 3, 1979 (Box 97, Folder 1)
      includes notes
    - Radio Transcript - Unedited: "The Subject is Peacemaking", May 21, 1987 (Box 97, Folder 2)
      KWMU Radio - NPR in St. Louis
    - Ramsey Clark, August 1970 (Box 97, Folder 3)
    - Religion in Politics, 1960-1963 (Box 97, Folder 4)
    - River Falls Journal, 1963 (Box 97, Folder 5)
      River Falls, Wisconsin
    - River Falls Journal - Sportscene, 1956-1957 (Box 97, Folder 6)
      Laue's sports column
    - United States Institute of Peace, 1985 (Box 97, Folder 7)
    - University of Missouri-St. Louis (UMSL) Current, Issue 393 - "Laue Receives Thomas Jefferson Award", March 26, 1981 (Box 97, Folder 8)
    - UMSL In Focus, 1977 (Box 97, Folder 9)
    - Virginia Beach Greekfest Riots, 1989-1990 (Box 97, Folder 10)
    - Washington University-St. Louis - Student Life Digest, 1971-1972 (Box 97, Folder 11)
    - Weathermen, Job Corps, and Lost Poverty Funds, 1968-1970 (Box 97, Folder 12)
    - Wisconsin State University-River Falls - Student Voice, May 24, 1970 (Box 97, Folder 13)
      includes article on Laue's commencement speech
- Series 8: Photographs, 1942-1992
  This series contains mostly black-and-white photographs of Laue from youth through adulthood. The series contains several portraits as well as pictures of Laue with fellow students, family members, and colleagues.
  - Commission on Proposals for the National Academy of Peace, ca. 1979-1982 (Box 97, Folder 14)
    9 black and white photographs featuring Laue and other Commission members, including Hawaii Senator Sparks Matsunaga
  - Fisk University Race Relations Institute, 1960 (Box 97, Folder 15)
    5 black and white photos, 1 color postcard
  - Friends and Colleagues, ca. mid 1980s - early 1990s (Box 97, Folder 16)
    1 black and whit photo, 2 color photos of Laue and colleagues
  - James Laue as a Student with Two Others, ca. 1960 (Box 98, Folder 1)
  - James Laue at Age 5 Sitting with Siblings Donald Roy and Annabelle Jean Laue, July 1942 (Box 98, Folder 2)
  - James Laue, Commencement Speaker, August 3, 1986 (Box 98, Folder 3)
  - Partners for Democratic Change, ca. 1992 (Box 98, Folder 4)
    3 color photos
  - Peace Circuit Rider - Earl Miner (in PAC Drawer), undated (Box 98, Folder 5)
    5 black and white photos of man in space-age three-wheeled go cart
  - Portrait Enclosed with Bio of Thomas Jefferson, ca. 1981 (Box 98, Folder 6)
  - Portraits, ca. 1978-1982 (Box 98, Folder 7)
    6 portraits of Laue, mostly from the Peace Commission era
  - Psychology Conference, Clark University, September 1909 (Box 98, Folder 8)
    postcard featuring numerous famous psychologists, sociologists, and anthropologists at conference
  - Quebec Conference, June 22-29, 1991 (Box 98, Folder 9)
    color photograph of attendees
- Series 9: Memorabilia, 1949-1993
  This series contains certificates, drawings, posters, and other memorabilia mostly from Laue's youth. Included are several items from Laue's participation in the Wisconsin American Legion Badger Boys civic activism program as a child.
  - Badger Boys State Merit Certificate and Memorabilia, 1954 (Box 98, Folder 10)
    includes a Badger Boys Citizens Manual, some badges and merit certificates, hand drawn voting signs, and an American Legion hat
  - Drawings by Laue's Uncle William G. Fortune, 1949 (Box 98, Folder 11)
    5 color drawings and collages; subjects include horses, landscapes, famous comedians, and a self-portrait
  - George Mason University Certificate of Appreciation for Five Years' Service, April 7, 1993 (Box 98, Folder 12)
    embossed certificate signed by George Johnson
  - Jimmy Carter Campaign Fan, Plains, Georgia, ca. 1980 (Box 98, Folder 13)
    cardboard fan with wooden handle advertising Jimmy Carter's presidential campaign
  - Poster for GMU Event, "In the Words of Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.," a celebration, January 1991 (Box 98, Folder 14)
    featuring Laue's reflections on personal experiences with MLK
- Series 10: Audio Cassettes, 1968-1991
  This series contains audio tape recordings of James Laue, Jimmy Carter, and Martin Luther King, Jr.
  - Carter - NCPCR, 1991 (Box 99, Folder 1)
    Jimmy Carter speaking at the National Conference on Peace and Conflict Resolution
  - Iowa Peace Institute, April 1993 (Box 99, Folder 2)
    Laue speaking at a conference
  - MLK, April 3, 1968 (Box 99, Folder 3)
    excerpts from Martin Luther King, Jr. speaking in Memphis on the eve of his assassination
  - "Making Ethical Decisions - Dilemmas for the Third Party," part 1 of 2, October 22, 1990 (Box 99, Folder 4)
    Laue giving guest lecture for CONF 643
  - "Making Ethical Decisions - Dilemmas for the Third Party," part 2 of 2, October 22, 1990 (Box 99, Folder 5)
  - St. Stephen's United Methodist Church, November 1988 (Box 99, Folder 6)
    Laue delivering sermon
- Series 11: Oversize, 1960-1980
  This series contains newspapers and large format magazines mostly dealing with racial issues, protest, and civil rights.
  - Ebony, November 1963 (Box 100, Folder 1)
    10x13" magazine
  - Ebony, March 1968 (Box 100, Folder 2)
  - Ebony, April 12, 1968 (Box 100, Folder 3)
  - Ebony, April 12, 1968 (Box 100, Folder 4)
  - Ebony, April 19, 1968 (Box 100, Folder 5)
  - Ebony, May 1968 (Box 100, Folder 6)
  - Ebony, April 1969 (Box 100, Folder 7)
  - Ebony, August 1970 (Box 100, Folder 8)
  - Ebony, August 1975 (Box 100, Folder 9)
  - Look, March 23, 1965 (Box 100, Folder 10)
  - U.S. News and World Report, June 2, 1980 (Box 100, Folder 11)
    8.5x11" magazine
  - Harvard Crimson, April 27, 1971 (Box 100, Folder 12)
    newspaper
  - The Miami Times, August 27, 1960 (Box 100, Folder 13)
  - New York Times - A Special Supplement: "The Trouble with Black Power" by Christopher Lasch, February 29, 1968 (Box 100, Folder 14)
    news clipping
  - Palante Latin Revolutionary News Service, November 20, 1970 (Box 100, Folder 15)
  - The Young Socialist - Boycott Woolworth's, April 1960 (Box 100, Folder 16)